<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/Schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/Schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Lion and the Jackal (version 2)</title>
                <editor ref="p:Dornan24" role="collector">Samuel Shaw Dornan</editor><editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="informant">	- unidentified -</editor><funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
                <principal>
                    <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
                    <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>XML templates, digitization infrastructure, and automated inline tagging</resp>
                    <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>
                <measure unit="KB" quantity="9">About 9 kilobytes</measure>
            </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
                <idno type="FFDB">NAF000458</idno>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://rightsstatements.org/vocab/InC-EDU/1.0/">In Copyright - Educational Use Permitted</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Dornan, Samuel S. (1917): The Tati Bushmen (Masarwas) and their Language. In: Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute 47, 37-112, pp. 76.</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly (or via the proxy of an interpreter or other immediate intermediary)
                    from an informant who either lived or grew up as a member of a culture whose
                    primary subsistence at the time of recording was or until recently had been
                    hunting, gathering, and/or fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the
                    recording and the relative freedom from external cultural influences. To create
                    a corpus with high representability, multiple versions of the same narrative
                    were omitted, cultural clusters and close cultural relations between two groups
                    were negatively taken into account, and it was aimed for the highest degree of
                    diversity.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="">
                    <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="21">Used to mark animal names in the text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="0">Used to mark plant names in the text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="0">Used to mark color names (adjectives and nouns) in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="0">Used to mark culturally important characters in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="0">Used to mark named places in the text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="0">Used to mark comments or any asides during a narrative.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="1">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
                    <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
                    <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> are <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">
                        Wikidata</orgName> Q-IDs and refer to their entry.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
                    <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to glossary entries
                        collected in the FFDB.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
                <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occuring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) with no clear systematic.</p>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>In-text explanations by the original editor are set in brackets. In-text
                        additions/excursions by the informant are set in parenthesis.</p>
                    <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to hide language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <quotation marks="all">
                    <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark quoted
                        passages up as <gi>quote</gi>.</p>
                </quotation>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged with a semantic tagger based on WordNet and on word lists as well as
                        subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>animal</gi> , <gi>
                        plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi> and <gi>placeName</gi>,
                        respectively.</p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="culture" key="CAF00208">Kua</name>
                    <date notAfter="1910" notBefore="1900" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1900 and 1910.</date>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        <textClass><keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI"><list><item><idno type="TMI">K361.1</idno><term>K361.1. Jackal ordered to take meat to lion's family takes it to his own.</term></item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
<p>A <animal latin="Felis leo">lion</animal> and a <animal latin="Canis mesomelas">jackal</animal> went to hunt one day. They came in sight of a lot of <animal latin="Taurotragus oryx">elands</animal>, and the <animal latin="Felis leo">lion</animal> shot with his bow and missed his <animal>buck</animal>. Then the <animal latin="Canis mesomelas">jackal</animal> tried and hit his <animal latin="Taurotragus oryx">eland</animal>. The <animal latin="Felis leo">lion</animal> was angry and called out, "I have hit, you haves missed." Now the <animal latin="Canis mesomelas">jackal</animal> was afraid, and agreed with the <animal latin="Felis leo">lion</animal> and said, "Yes, you have hit." After that they went home to have a sleep, intending to come back, to cut up the meat. As soon as the <animal latin="Felis leo">lion</animal> was asleep, the <animal latin="Canis mesomelas">jackal</animal> went back to the dead <animal>buck</animal>, and tearing out its belly crawled into it, and began to eat all the best part of the fat round the heart.</p>
<p>The <animal latin="Felis leo">lion</animal> awoke and immediately came to the carcase, and saw the <animal latin="Canis mesomelas">jackal</animal>'s tail sticking out of the dead <animal latin="Taurotragus oryx">eland</animal>. So the <animal latin="Felis leo">lion</animal> caught him by the tail, and swung him out, and ordered him to stand at a distance. Afterwards the <animal latin="Felis leo">lion</animal> gave the <animal latin="Canis mesomelas">jackal</animal> some small pieces of meat to eat, and told him to take some of the best of the fat to the <animal latin="Felis leo">lion</animal>'s wife and children, but the <animal latin="Canis mesomelas">jackal</animal> took the fat to his own wife and children, and then he fled quite away with his own wife and children to another part of the country. <epimyth>The tale is ended.</epimyth></p>
</body></text>
</TEI>
