<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Why the Bushmen Don't Sleep with the Moon in Their Faces</title>
        <editor ref="p:Dornan24" role="collector">Samuel Shaw Dornan</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="informant">unidentified</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML templates, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="8">About 8 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NAF000465</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://rightsstatements.org/vocab/InC-EDU/1.0/">In Copyright - Educational Use Permitted</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2023">2023</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Dornan, Samuel S. (1917): The Tati Bushmen (Masarwas) and their Language. In: Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute 47, 37-112. Quot. pp. 80-81.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from an informant who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="">
          <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="1">Used to mark animal names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="0">Used to mark plant names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="0">Used to mark colors (adjectives and nouns) mentioned in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="0">Used to mark personal names (usually characters)
                        mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="0">Used to mark named place names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="1">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="0">Used to mark comments or asides within the course of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="1">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged using a semantic tagger based on WordNet and self-provided word
                        lists, and were subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>
                        animal</gi>, <gi>plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, and <gi>
                        placeName</gi>, respectively.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CAF00208">Kua</name>
          <date notAfter="1910" notBefore="1900" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1900 and 1910.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI">
          <!-- link to our TMI once its online -->
          <list>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">C315.2</idno>
              <term>C315.2. Tabu: looking at heavenly body.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">H1400+KH</idno>
              <term>H1400+KH. Fear test: Snake sings, timid visitors do not answer, brave visitors do.</term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p><anamyth>The Bushmen never go to sleep with the moon in their faces. They never build their huts so that the moon shines in at the door. The reason for that I am now going to tell you.</anamyth> A long, long time ago, a number of Bushmen were encamped <pb n="81"/>near some water, where they had killed <animal>game</animal>. The water was much. They were there a long time. During the night when all were asleep, the moon came down to have a look at herself in the water. The moon often did this, but she did not like the Bushmen to see her. One of the Bushmen waking up, saw the moon washing herself in the water. The sight was very nice. So the man awoke some of his friends very quietly. They looked and they were pleased. They laughed softly. But while they were looking at the moon in the water, some of their enemies crept up behind, and before they could seize their weapons, killed them all. The enemies shouted much, and they took all the meat. <epimyth>That is the reason why we never sleep with the moon in our faces, lest this should happen over again, and some people say that if you sleep with the moon shining on you, you will wake up with a great pain in the face. This is the way the moon warns us not to sleep. It is the end of the tale.</epimyth></p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
