<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Origin of Marriage</title>
        <editor ref="p:Dornan24" role="collector">Samuel Shaw Dornan</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="informant">unidentified</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML templates, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="11">About 11 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NAF000462</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://rightsstatements.org/vocab/InC-EDU/1.0/">In Copyright - Educational Use Permitted</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2023">2023</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Dornan, Samuel S. (1917): The Tati Bushmen (Masarwas) and their Language. In: Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute 47, 37-112. Quot. pp. 78-79.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from an informant who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="">
          <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="2">Used to mark animal names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="10">Used to mark plant names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="0">Used to mark colors (adjectives and nouns) mentioned in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="0">Used to mark personal names (usually characters)
                        mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="0">Used to mark named place names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="1">Used to mark comments or asides within the course of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="1">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged using a semantic tagger based on WordNet and self-provided word
                        lists, and were subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>
                        animal</gi>, <gi>plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, and <gi>
                        placeName</gi>, respectively.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CAF00209">Hiecheware</name>
          <date notAfter="1910" notBefore="1900" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1900 and 1910.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI">
          <!-- link to our TMI once its online -->
          <list>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">A1352</idno>
              <term>A1352. Origin of sexual intercourse.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">A1555</idno>
              <term>A1555. Origin of marriage.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">F566.1</idno>
              <term>F566.1. Village of men only.</term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>In the beginning of things, a long, long time ago, when the men and women of the early race lived upon the earth, <apartmyth>so my father told me</apartmyth>, the men lived by hunting and the women by gathering <plant>grass seeds</plant>. They lived on opposite sides of a big river. In this river there grew a great quantity of <plant>reeds</plant>, in which the women gathered the <plant>seeds</plant>. One day the men went out shooting with their bows and poisoned arrows and killed a <animal>springbuck</animal>. They had no fire to cook the meat, as they had carelessly let their fire go out. They were not like the women, who always carried some fire, and did things nicely. The men often took a long time get the fire alight again. This day they were so hungry that they could not wait, and so they sent one of their number down to the river to get some fire from the women. Now there were five of them. When the man got down to the river, and went across, he found a woman amongst the <plant>reeds</plant> gathering <plant>grass seeds</plant>, and he asked her for some fire. She said to him: "Come to my place, and I will give you some." When they arrived at the village they went into one of the huts, and the woman told him to wait until she had crushed the <plant>grass seeds</plant>, and then she would give him some fire. So he sat down and waited. The woman got her stone and pounded up the <plant>seeds</plant>; then she put the <plant>seeds</plant> into a pot and made some porridge. After it was cooked she gave some of it to the man, and he asked her what it was, and she said it was porridge. "Well," said he, "it is very nice food, and I shall just stay with you." So he did not go back to his companions with the fire.</p>
      <p>After waiting a long time, the men, who were beginning to feel hungry by this time, sent another of their number down to the river to get fire. He also met a woman gathering <plant>grass seeds</plant>, and he told her he had come for some fire. She told him to wait until her return to her hut, when she would give him some fire. He <pb n="79"/>waited. She also made some porridge, and gave him a share of it, and he said the food was nice, so he quite forgot to go back with the fire.</p>
      <p>Next a third man was sent with the same message. He also got down to the river and found a woman amongst the <plant>reeds</plant>. He told her he had come to get some fire, for their own fire had gone out, and they were very hungry. He did not say anything about the other two men, as he was so very much afraid. The woman said to him: "If you will come to my village I will give you some fire." He went with her, and she made some fire and cooked porridge. He was quite pleased with the food, and said it was very nice. So he also quite forgot to go back with the fire.</p>
      <p>Now there were only two men left. They began to get very frightened. They did not know why their companions had not come back with the fire. There were many evil spirits in those days, and they thought their friends might be killed. They began to quarrel, and one of them said to the other: "Wait here till I go and try to get some fire from the women over yonder." So he went away: the other man waited. But he met a woman near the river, and he returned with her to her village, and did not come back to his companion. By this time many days had gone by, and the <animal>springbuck</animal> was getting quite rotten, for it was very hot weather, and the last man was getting very hungry. So he waited a long time, but his friend never came back. He took up his bow and arrows and fled into the far country, and was lost altogether. <epimyth>This is how marriage came amongst men and women, and it is the end of the tale.</epimyth></p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
