<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Bootoolgah the Crane and Goonur the Kangaroo Rat, the Fire Makers</title>
        <editor ref="p:Parker1451" role="collector">K. Langloh Parker</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="informant">unidentified</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML templates, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="21">About 21 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NIP028735</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial (CC BY-NC)</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2023">2023</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Parker, K. Langloh (1896): Australian Legendary Tales. Folk-Lore of the Noongahburrahs as Told by the Piccaninnies. With Introduction by Andrew Lang. Illustrations by a Native Artist, and Specimen of the Native Text. London: Nutt &amp; Melbourne: Melville, Mullen &amp; Slade. Quot. pp. 24-29.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from an informant who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="">
          <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="87">Used to mark animal names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="9">Used to mark plant names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="25">Used to mark colors (adjectives and nouns) mentioned in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="0">Used to mark personal names (usually characters)
                        mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="0">Used to mark named place names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="0">Used to mark comments or asides within the course of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged using a semantic tagger based on WordNet and self-provided word
                        lists, and were subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>
                        animal</gi>, <gi>plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, and <gi>
                        placeName</gi>, respectively.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CIPD0270">Yuwaalaraay</name>
          <date notAfter="1895" notBefore="1875" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1875 and 1895.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI">
          <!-- link to our TMI once its online -->
          <list>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">A1414.1</idno>
              <term>A1414.1. Origin of fire &#8211; rubbing sticks.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">A1415</idno>
              <term>A1415. Theft of fire. Mankind is without fire. A culture hero steals it from the owner.</term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>In the days when <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal>, the <animal>crane</animal>, married <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal>, the <animal>kangaroo rat</animal>, there was no fire in their country. They had to eat their food raw or just dry it in the sun. One day when <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> was rubbing two pieces of wood together, he saw a faint spark sent forth and then a slight smoke. "Look," he said to <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal>, "see what comes when I rub these pieces of wood together - smoke! Would it not be good if we could make fire for ourselves with which to cook our food, so as not to have to wait for the sun to dry it?"</p>
      <p><animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> looked, and, seeing the smoke, she said: "Great indeed would be the day when we could make fire. Split your stick, <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal>, and place in the opening bark and <plant>grass</plant> that even one spark may kindle a <color>light</color>." And hearing wisdom in her words, even as she said <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> did. And lo! after much rubbing, from the opening came a small flame. For as <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> had said it would, the spark lit the <plant>grass</plant>, the bark smouldered and smoked, and so <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> <pb n="25"/>the <animal>crane</animal>, and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> the <animal>kangaroo rat</animal>, discovered the art of fire making.</p>
      <p>"This we will keep secret," they said, "from all the tribes. When we make a fire to cook our <animal>fish</animal> we will go into a <plant><ref target="g:GIP0247.010">Bingahwingul</ref></plant> scrub. There we will make a fire and cook our food in secret. We will hide our firesticks in the open-mouthed seeds of the <plant><ref target="g:GIP0247.010">Bingahwinguls</ref></plant>; one firestick we will carry always hidden in our <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref>."</p>
      <p><animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> cooked the next <animal>fish</animal> they caught, and found it very good. When they went back to the camp they took some of their cooked <animal>fish</animal> with them. The <color>blacks</color> noticed it looked quite different from the usual sun-dried <animal>fish</animal>, so they asked: " What did you to that <animal>fish</animal>?</p>
      <p>"Let it lie in the sun," said they.</p>
      <p>"Not so," said the others.</p>
      <p>But that the <animal>fish</animal> was sun-dried <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> persisted. Day by day passed, and after catching their <animal>fish</animal>, these two always disappeared, returning with their food looking quite different from that of the others. At last, being unable to extract any information from them, it was determined by the tribe to watch them. <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.015">Boolooral</ref></animal>, the <animal>night owl</animal>, and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.116">Quarrian</ref></animal>, the <animal>parrot</animal>, were appointed to follow the two when they disappeared, to watch where they went, and find out what they did. Accordingly, after the next <animal>fish</animal> were caught, when <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> gathered up their share and started for the <plant>bush</plant>, <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.015">Boolooral</ref></animal> and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.116">Quarrian</ref></animal> followed on their tracks. They saw them disappear into a <plant><ref target="g:GIP0247.010">Bingahwingul</ref></plant> scrub, where they lost sight of them. Seeing a high <plant>tree</plant> on the edge of the scrub, they climbed up it, and from there they saw all that was to be seen. They saw <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> throw down <pb n="26"/>their load of <animal>fish</animal>, open their <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref> and take from it a stick, which stick, when they had blown upon it, they laid in the midst of a heap of leaves and twigs, and at once from this heap they saw a flame leap, which flame the fire makers fed with bigger sticks. Then, as the flame died down, they saw the two place their <animal>fish</animal> in the ashes that remained from the burnt sticks. Then back to the camp of their tribes went <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.015">Boolooral</ref></animal> and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.116">Quarrian</ref></animal>, back with the news of their discovery. Great was the talk amongst the <color>blacks</color>, and many the queries as to how to get possession of the <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref> with the fire stick in it, when next <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> came into the camp. It was at length decided to hold a <ref target="g:GIP0247.037">corrobboree</ref>, and it was to be one on a scale not often seen, probably never before by the young of the tribes. The <color>grey</color> beards proposed to so astonish <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> as to make them forget to guard their precious <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref>. As soon as they were intent on the <ref target="g:GIP0247.037">corrobboree</ref> and off guard, some one was to seize the <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref>, steal the firestick and start fires for the good of all. Most of them had tasted the cooked <animal>fish</animal> brought into the camp by the fire makers and, having found it good, hungered for it. <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.002">Beeargah</ref></animal>, the <animal>hawk</animal>, was told to feign sickness, to tie up his head, and to lie down near wherever the two sat to watch the <ref target="g:GIP0247.037">corrobboree</ref>. Lying near them, he was to watch them all the time, and when they were laughing and unthinking of anything but the spectacle before them, he was to steal the <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref>. Having arranged their plan of action, they all prepared for a big <ref target="g:GIP0247.037">corrobboree</ref>. They sent word to all the surrounding tribes, asking them to attend, especially they begged the <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.022">Bralgahs</ref></animal> to come, as they were celebrated for their wonderful dancing, which was so wonderful <pb n="27"/>as to be most likely to absorb the attention of the fire makers.</p>
      <p>All the tribes agreed to come, and soon all were engaged in great preparations. Each determined to outdo the other in the quaintness and brightness of their painting for the <ref target="g:GIP0247.037">corrobboree</ref>. Each tribe as they arrived gained great applause; never before had the young people seen so much diversity in colouring and design. <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.003">Beeleer</ref></animal>, the <animal><color>Black</color> Cockatoo</animal> tribe, came with <color>bright</color> splashes of <color>orange-red</color> on their <color>black</color> skins. The <animal>Pelicans</animal> came as a contrast, almost pure <color>white</color>, only a touch here and there of their <color>black</color> skin showing where the <color>white</color> paint had rubbed off. The <animal><color>Black</color> Divers</animal> came in their <color>black</color> skins, but these polished to shine like satin. Then came the <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.093">Millears</ref></animal>, the beauties of the <animal>Kangaroo Rat</animal> family, who had their home on the <ref target="g:GIP0247.100">Morillas</ref>. After them came the <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.024">Buckandeer</ref></animal> or Native <animal>Cat</animal> tribe, painted in <color>dull colours</color>, but in all sorts of patterns. <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.088">Mairas</ref></animal> or <animal>Paddymelons</animal> came too in haste to take part in the great <ref target="g:GIP0247.037">corrobboree</ref>. After them, walking slowly, came the <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.022">Bralgahs</ref></animal>, looking tall and dignified as they held up their <color>red</color> heads, painted so in contrast to their <pb n="28"/><color>French-grey</color> bodies, which they deemed too dull a <color>colour</color>, unbrightened, for such a gay occasion. Amongst the many tribes there, too numerous to mention, were the <color>rose</color> and <color>grey</color> painted <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.058">Galahs</ref></animal>, the <color>green</color> and <color>crimson</color> painted <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.008">Billai</ref></animal>: most brilliant were they with their bodies <color>grass green</color> and their sides <color>bright crimson</color>, so afterwards gaining them the name of <animal><color>crimson</color> wings</animal>. The <color>bright</color> little <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.060">Gidgereegahs</ref></animal> came too.</p>
      <p>Great was the gathering that <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal>, the <animal>crane</animal>, and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal>, the <animal>kangaroo rat</animal>, found assembled as they hurried on to the scene. <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> had warned <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> that they must only be spectators, and take no active part in the <ref target="g:GIP0247.037">corrobboree</ref>, as they had to guard their combee. Obedient to his advice, <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> seated herself beside him and slung the <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref> over her arm. <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> warned her to be careful and not forget she had it. But as the <ref target="g:GIP0247.037">corrobboree</ref> went on, so absorbed did she become that she forgot the <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref>, which slipped from her arm. Happily, <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> saw it do so, replaced it, and bade her take heed, so baulking <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.002">Beeargah</ref></animal>, who had been about to seize it, for his vigilance was unceasing, and, deeming him sick almost unto death, the two whom lie was watching took no heed of him. Back he crouched, moaning as he turned, but keeping ever an eye on <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal>. And soon was he rewarded. Now came the turn of the <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.022">Bralgahs</ref></animal> to dance, and every eye but that of the watchful one was fixed on them as slowly they came into the ring. First they advanced, bowed and retired, then they repeated what they had done before, and again, each time getting faster and faster in their movements, changing their bows into pirouettes, craning their long necks and making such antics as they went through <pb n="29"/>the figures of their dance, and replacing their dignity with such grotesqueness, as to make their large audience shake with laughter, they themselves keeping throughout all their grotesque measures a solemn air, which only seemed to heighten the effect of their antics.</p>
      <p>And now came the chance of <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.002">Beeargah</ref></animal> the <animal>hawk</animal>. In the excitement of the moment <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> forgot the <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref>, as did <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal>. They joined in the mirthful applause of the crowd, and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal> threw herself back helpless with laughter. As she did so the <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref> slipped from her arm. Then up jumped the sick man from behind her, seized the <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref> with his <ref target="g:GIP0247.034">combo</ref>, cut it open, snatched forth the firestick, set fire to the heap of <plant>grass</plant> ready near where he had lain, and all before the two realised their loss. When they discovered the precious <ref target="g:GIP0247.033">comebee</ref> was gone, up jumped <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal> and <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.074">Goonur</ref></animal>. After <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.002">Beeargah</ref></animal> ran <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal>, but <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.002">Beeargah</ref></animal> had a start and was fleeter of foot, so distanced his pursuer quickly. As he ran he fired the <plant>grass</plant> with the stick he still held. <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.017">Bootoolgah</ref></animal>, finding he could not catch <animal><ref target="g:GIP0247.002">Beeargah</ref></animal>, and seeing fires everywhere, retired from the pursuit, feeling it was useless now to try and guard their secret, for it had now become the common property of all the tribes there assembled.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
