<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#8231;aua&#7499;&#275;</title>
        <editor ref="p:Boas15" role="collector">Franz Boas</editor>
        <editor ref="p:Haia&#322;k&#8231;&#238;ngam&#275;&#7499;1002" role="informant">Hai&#700;a&#322;k&#8231;&#238;ngam&#275;&#7499;</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML templates, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="38">About 38 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NNA019439</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial (CC BY-NC)</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2023">2023</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Boas, Franz (1910): Kwakiutl Tales. New York: Columbia University Press (Columbia University Contributions to Anthropology, 2). Quot. pp. 8-38.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from an informant who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="">
          <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="93">Used to mark animal names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="7">Used to mark plant names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="4">Used to mark colors (adjectives and nouns) mentioned in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="55">Used to mark personal names (usually characters)
                        mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="37">Used to mark named place names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="0">Used to mark comments or asides within the course of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="1">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged using a semantic tagger based on WordNet and self-provided word
                        lists, and were subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>
                        animal</gi>, <gi>plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, and <gi>
                        placeName</gi>, respectively.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CNA29001">Kwakwaka&#700;wakw</name>
          <date when="1897" type="recorded">Recorded in 1897.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>A person living at <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName> dreamed. [He said] "Don't stay thus, children! I have dreamed of the supernatural power that we get from time to time [we inherit]." Thus he said. He wakened his children. Then the children arose. He instructed his children, [saying] that he had dreamed of the place where he always found dead <animal>animals</animal> on account of the one-horned mountain-<animal>goat</animal>, the large mountain-<animal>goat</animal>, that only mother of the mountain-<animal>goats</animal>. [He said,] "Go on, go on, start, children! Go to our place at <placeName>K&#183;&#257;&#700;t&#226;l&#275;</placeName>." <placeName>K&#183;&#257;&#700;t&#226;l&#275;</placeName> was the name of the place where he found dead <animal>animals</animal> on account of the one-horned mountain-<animal>goat</animal>. Then his children went up the river of <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName>. They arrived at the place of their father, <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName>. <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName> was the name of their father.</p>
      <p>Then the children started. They were four. Four were their <animal>dogs</animal>, all hunting-<animal>dogs</animal>. Then they sat down on the bank of the river. They were sitting there and looking <pb n="11"/>about over the country. The eldest one of the children saw something <color>white</color> on a meadow. "What may that be, friends?" said he to his younger brothers. "Evidently that is what our father referred to. Evidently that is the thing about which our father gave us instructions." Then it was shown to the <animal>dog</animal>. The <animal>dog</animal> discovered the <color>white</color> thing on the meadow. The <animal>dog</animal> went to the meadow. The <animal>dog</animal> started. The <animal>dog</animal> reached the <color>white</color> thing on the meadow, and barked, barking at the <color>white</color> thing on the meadow. Then the owners of the <animal>dog</animal> spoke. "Evidently that is what we came here for." Thus said the children.</p>
      <p>The <animal>dog</animal> came back to his master. Then the <animal>dog</animal> raised his head to his master. They say the <animal>dog</animal> probably knew about the mountain-<animal>goat</animal> lying dead on the meadow. Then the brothers started, and the oldest one tried to get ahead of the others, although the youngest advised his elder brothers, [saying,] "Don't walk too fast, friends!" Thus said the youngest one to his elder brothers. Then the youngest one tried to speak again. "Take heed of the advice of our father!" Thus said the youngest one. He, the youngest one, alone spoke wisely. The eldest one arrived at the place where the large one-horned mountain-<animal>goat</animal> was lying dead on the meadow. The mountain-<animal>goat</animal> had a piece of quartz standing on its forehead. Then the eldest brother desired it overmuch. That eldest one twisted off the quartz from One-Horn. "Y&#228;," said the youngest one. He, the youngest one, alone spoke wisely, trying to advise his elder brothers. Then the elder ones began to skin it. They skinned it quickly. Only the youngest one warned his elder brothers; but they disobeyed the instructions of their father, although the father tried to instruct his children [well].</p>
      <p>The elder brothers were quick, and they quickly took off the tallow. Then they cut open [the mountain-goat] <pb n="13"/>to take off the kidney-fat. The elder brothers tried to get everything; but the youngest one was just sitting on the meadow, because he felt badly on account of his elder brothers, who overstepped the advice that their father had tried to give them in regard to their actions. The elder ones tried to get all the fat of the intestines of the one-horned mountain-<animal>goat</animal>. Then the youngest one spoke. "Be quick before anything happens, slaves [of misfortune]! Something important is going on above in the sky." Then a fog appeared above. In vain the elder brothers fought among themselves for the fat of the intestines, and for all the kidney-fat, and for the skin of the mountain-<animal>goat</animal>. In vain they tied it up quickly. Then they saw the sky. Smoke was rolling down the mountains. Evidently it was going to snow. Then it began to snow from above.</p>
      <p>The youngest one just pinched off a little of the fat of the intestines, and then he also pinched off a little of the kidney-fat, which he kept in his mouth, - the youngest one. The youngest one continued to speak wisely. He followed the instructions of the father to his children, for the father knew what the ancestors of <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName> had been doing. The youngest one said to his elder brothers, "Make a start, slaves (of misfortune)." They started again and again [to go back]. Then a very heavy fall of snow came down. The snow kept on coming down. The youngest one did not carry anything, Only the elder brothers carried much on their backs; but the youngest one just followed the words of his father, that had been given as advice by the father to his children, although be had repeated it often when he tried to instruct his children, and when <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName> told them much about his ancestors.</p>
      <p>The brothers were all coming down, the youngest one <pb n="15"/>in the rear. The youngest one just thought that his elder brothers would be unlucky. In vain the brothers cried, because they were afraid of the snow. Then the snow reached the top of their feet. Then the snow reached up to their necks. They just sat down, and they would cry on account of what might happen. Only the youngest one did not cry in vain. He was only sad because he had in vain tried to speak wisely to his elder brothers, because he tried to follow the instructions of his father to his children.</p>
      <p>They were coming [down], and arrived at a gorge on the mountain. A brook was trickling down there. Their trail led along under the brook, [which was falling down] from an overhanging cliff, so that the trail led along under it. Then they sat down by the dripping brook, and they cried, for what could they do? for the <plant>bushes</plant> were covered to the top by the snow. They reached the dripping brook on account of the <animal>dogs</animal>, for the <animal>dogs</animal> made a trail for their masters, and the <animal>dogs</animal> marked [a trail] along the snow for their masters. They were followed by their masters, [who went] on the trail of the <animal>dogs</animal>. Therefore they arrived at the place where they were going to endure hardships. Then the brothers were just crying on the rocks, for they could not do anything because their trail was all ice, for it was really overhanging, - the place under which the children had to go along.</p>
      <p>Then the youngest one spoke to his elder brothers. Then he blamed his elder brothers. "Oh, you who disagree with me!" he said to his elder brothers, "why did you do that, although our father tried to advise us?" Thus said the youngest one to his elder brothers. He just scorned his elder brothers because the elder children were just crying. Then it occurred to the eldest one to send his <animal>dog</animal> over the rocks to start along the trail. There <pb n="17"/>was snow on top of the ice, and there was ice on the trail. The <animal>dog</animal> started across. Then an accident happened to the <animal>dog</animal> of the eldest brother, and the <animal>dog</animal> of the eldest brother tumbled down. He dropped into the gorge, and he was dead. Then the eldest brother cried in vain on account of what had happened to his <animal>dog</animal>, who fell down and dropped into the gorge. Then the <animal>dog</animal> of the next eldest brother also made an attempt. The <animal>dog</animal> of the third brother also walked on it. They just did the same as the <animal>dog</animal> of the eldest brother. The <animal>dog</animal> of the third brother just dropped into the gorge. Then the <animal>dog</animal> of the one next to the youngest tried to walk. He did just the same as the <animal>dog</animal> of his brother. The <animal>dog</animal> of the one next to the youngest had an accident.</p>
      <p>Then the eldest one spoke. "Let me try and go along the trail." Thus said the eldest one to his younger brothers. "Go on, and try!" said the younger brothers to their elder brother. Then the eldest brother tried to go across. He walked on the ice, and just the same happened to him as to the <animal>dogs</animal>. That man just dropped down into the gorge, to the same place to which the <animal>dogs</animal> had dropped. Then his younger brothers cried in vain. The second one went across on the trail; and just the same thing happened to him, he dropped into the gorge; and the same thing also happened to the other one, he just dropped into the gorge. Then the three men and their <animal>dogs</animal> were all dead.</p>
      <p>The youngest one alone was alive. He sat on the rock and cried on account of his elder brothers. The boy had half a mind to go on and just die, together with his dear elder brothers. He was crying. The boy cried on account of his elder brothers, and the <animal>dog</animal>, howled. The <animal>dog</animal> was crying with his master. Then the boy stopped crying, and directed his mind to a thing on <pb n="19"/>the rock. The <animal>dog</animal>, however, almost [not] spoke to his master. The <animal>dog</animal> would go and nudge his master, who was sitting on the rock, as though the <animal>dog</animal> would hurry his master to walk along the rock. After a little while it stopped snowing.</p>
      <p>Then the <animal>dog</animal> of the youngest one tried to cross on the rock. The <animal>dog</animal> held on to the edge of the rock where the ice was at the overhanging place. The <animal>dog</animal> went safely across the ice. Then he came back and went straight to his master and nudged him, as though he were saying to his master, "Don't stay in this manner!" Then the <animal>dog</animal> hurried his master. Then the boy thought that he would listen to his <animal>dog</animal>, for his <animal>dog</animal> almost [not] spoke to him. Only he did not understand what the <animal>dog</animal> said to his master. Then the boy arose on the rock and lay on the back of his <animal>dog</animal>. He held on to the back of his <animal>dog</animal>, who then went across the ice. Then he was taken across the ice by his <animal>dog</animal>. Thus the boy went across, being carried across by his <animal>dog</animal>. Then the boy and his <animal>dog</animal> were safe.</p>
      <p>He still held in his mouth the tallow that he had pinched off. Four pieces were held by him in his mouth. He had only cut off a little from the skin of the one-horned one. He had just put that skin of the one-horned mountain-<animal>goat</animal> in his armpit. Then the <animal>dog</animal> just put his master down on the rock, and he just sat down at the place where they had endured hardships. The <animal>dog</animal> went on marking the way downward, making a trail for his master through the snow, and then he returned to his master every time he had finished making a trail through the snow for his master. Only [by] doing like this repeatedly did the <animal>dog</animal> go on, continuing down his trail through the snow for his master, and coming back every time, asking his master [to go on]. The <animal>dog</animal> came down, <pb n="21"/>continuing his trail downward through the snow, and in this manner almost arrived at the river.</p>
      <p>Then the boy was tired out. He came to the bank of the river, and the <animal>dog</animal> went down the river. His mind was just one with that of the <animal>dog</animal>; and the <animal>dog</animal> was thinking of the village, and he was also thinking of the man. In this manner he just tried to bring his master home to the house at a place called <placeName>Q!aw&#257;&#700;k&#183;as</placeName>. There is a fishing-station of the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la at <placeName>Q!aw&#257;&#700;k&#183;as</placeName>; and it was as though the <animal>dog</animal> spoke to his master, that the <animal>dog</animal> thought of bringing his master to the fishing-place at <placeName>Q!aw&#257;&#700;k&#183;as</placeName>. Then the <animal>dog</animal> thought that he would swim and carry his master on his back [to swim] down the river [with his master], for the boy was tired out, as the snow covered the tops of the <plant>trees</plant>, and the <animal>dog</animal> was tired out from marking the way through the snow. Therefore he swam down the river with his master.</p>
      <p>They arrived at a house in which a man lived at <placeName>Q!aw&#257;&#700;k&#183;as</placeName>. That was what the <animal>dog</animal> had thought of. Then he just put his master down on the bank, but the boy could not walk well. The <animal>dog</animal> entered the house. Probably it had not been long since the owner of the house had gone down the stream with the current, frightened by the snow. The <animal>dog</animal> dug in the fireplace, and just bade his master sit in the hole at the fireplace; and he buried him and covered him with ashes. Only his mouth showed after he had buried his master. Thus he tried to warm his master. He just lay down, coiling himself around his master.</p>
      <p>The father wailed for his children because he thought that it had gone wrong with his children. He [only] gave up his children for lost when he saw the snow coming down; and he already thought that his children had <pb n="23"/>perished. Now it stopped snowing, after it had [just] snowed from morning till night. For just two days it had been snowing, and the snow reached the tops of the <plant>bushes</plant>. Then the father called his tribe and sat down with his tribe. He asked his tribe what to do. "What shall we do, my dear ones?" Thus he said to his tribe. "It may be that one of my children has survived." Then the tribe said that they would go and try to go up the river of <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName>. One of them said, "I wonder what we shall do! Shall we walk, or shall we go in a canoe?" Thus said one of the men. "Don't let us do that," said the one who spoke in the house. "Let us push down four planks. Let us continue to lay them down flat and put them down endwise, changing their positions. Let us take four and lay them down flat on the snow."</p>
      <p>They tried to pole up the river, but they just gave it up on account of the snow which was floating on the water. Then the tribe agreed to change the position of the planks, laying them down flat on the snow, while they were going up the river of <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName>. Then they put down the planks going up the river towards <placeName>Q!aw&#257;&#700;k&#183;as</placeName>. Then they arrived at a tributary. Then one man discovered an opening in the snow. "What may this be?" said the man. "Maybe a <animal>wolf</animal>," said the man, "which made this opening as a sign." Thus said the man while they approached the trail of the <animal>dog</animal>, - of that <animal>dog</animal> of the only one of the children of <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName> who was left, - which was the trail that the <animal>dog</animal> had made for his master, and that came down the river. The men just went in the tracks that the <animal>dog</animal> had made for his master. Then the tribe arrived at <placeName>Q!aw&#257;&#700;k&#183;as</placeName>, where the only one of the children of <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName> that was left over had stopped. They entered the house, and saw the child buried in the floor. Then the people <pb n="25"/>cried when they discovered the child, for only its mouth showed. Then the boy was pulled out by the men. The boy got out of the hole, and they saw his entire body. His feet were just falling off, for they and his fingers were frostbitten; and the skin of his whole body came off, for it was frozen. Therefore the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la just cried out of pity for the boy, for the boy looked ragged because he was frozen.</p>
      <p>Then they made up their minds what to do in case they should take the boy down the river, for he was not well enough to be handled roughly; for the boy was almost as though there were no life left in him, because he was frozen. Then the people tried to go down river. They cut two poles; and four men carried them, one at each end and the boy lay between them as they were carried at each end by the four men. They started and went home, walking on the boards, which were joined end to end.</p>
      <p>Then one man, his uncle, spoke, saying that they should leave the boy a while a little above the village, that the boy should stop there. Then his father was told that only one of his children was left. Then the father of the children, <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName>, spoke. "Indeed, that is what I said to my children. Don't let them bring this my child out of the woods." Then his father made up his mind what to do for the only one of his children who was still alive. <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName> thought that he would make a winter dance for the only one among his children who was still alive. The people did not say that one was still alive: they just said that they were all dead, for they kept it secret on account of what <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName> had said, because he was just going to show his great dance, the property of his family. It was to be the <animal>wolf</animal>-step for his child. It was to be the great dance from above, that would give his child supernatural power.</p>
      <p><pb n="27"/>Then he cleared his house. Then the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la just came stepping like <animal>wolves</animal> to the one who was still alive, who had encountered danger in hunting mountain-<animal>goats</animal>. Then the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la surrounded him; and the great supernatural one, the great dance from above, came stepping like <animal>wolves</animal>. That was the great dance from above of the ancient tribe at <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName>. Then the great dance from above came down to the beach from the woods, and the dancers entered the house. Many of the ancestors of the people of <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName>, the ancestors of the Thunder-<animal>Birds</animal>, danced the supernatural dance. They brought it into the house, and the great dance from above<note>See F. Boas, Social Organization and Secret Societies of the Kwakiutl Indians (Report of the U.S. National Museum for 1895, p. 477, also p. 382).</note> was just the great supernatural power of <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName> at <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName>.</p>
      <p>Then he showed what his child had taken from the great mountain-<animal>goat</animal>, the one-horned one, the tallow that he had pinched off, and which had just been kept in the mouth by his child. He put it on the floor of his house, and showed what had been held in the mouth. Then it increased in size, and the house of his father was very full. That was the supernatural treasure obtained from the one-horned one, that was valued, and that was obtained [found dead] from the large one-horned mountain-<animal>goat</animal>. What the boy had just held in his mouth was increasing in size: therefore that youngest boy was lucky, for he was not foolish, but had followed the advice of his father; but his elder brothers were dead.</p>
      <p>Then his father, <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName>, kept inviting [the people] all the time, for the supernatural treasure of his child had increased in size, that which his child had had in his mouth, the child of <persName>Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499;&#275;</persName>. Then his father <pb n="29"/>danced. It was the great dance, from above. That was the great dance from above of the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la, who lived at <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName>; and that was the song they sang first. Then they sang. The songs were sung because he had obtained supernatural power, the one who was endangered in hunting mountain-<animal>goats</animal> at Having Humpback-Salmon. Therefore he just turned into the great dance from above, - he, the only one who remained alive of those who were endangered in hunting mountain-<animal>goats</animal>. Therefore the great dance from above belongs to the great tribe at <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName>, and that came to those who were gathered at <placeName>Gwa&#700;dz&#275;&#7499;</placeName>, - those who had a winter dance together at <placeName>Gwa&#700;dz&#275;&#7499;</placeName>, and they came to be one when they came to dance the winter dance together at <placeName>Gwa&#700;dz&#275;&#7499;</placeName>.</p>
      <p>Then <persName>Copper-Maker-Face</persName> and <persName>Pearl-Maker-Face</persName> asked <persName>Wood-Carver</persName>, the ancestor of the Kwakiutl, the ancestor of the Wood-Carvers, to make a Showing-Teeth headdress [<animal>wolf</animal> head-dress] for the great dance from above. He was the ancestor of the clan K&#183;!&#238;g&#183;a&#275;&#700;nox&#7512;. Now they continually plaited ropes for leading the d&#7431;&#700;nts!&#275;q of the war-dance. Then <persName>Listened-to</persName> came and sat behind them when he learned about what is called "great dance from above" of the ancestors of the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la, when they were dancing the winter dance together at <placeName>Gwa&#700;dz&#275;&#7499;</placeName> at the north side of <placeName>G&#183;i&#333;&#700;x</placeName>.</p>
      <p>Then the clan sat down, looking among their children [to see] who among the ancestors of the K&#183;!&#238;g&#183;a&#275;&#700;nox&#7512;, the clan of the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la, should disappear. Then the boy was instructed: "just go into the water all the time in the lakes in the woods, and always sprinkle yourself with water. Rub your body with <plant>hemlock</plant>-branches four times." Thus the boy was told by his father and uncles. " Just go straight to the place named <placeName>Qwa&#7499;n&#275;qw&#257;&#700;la</placeName>, at the lake above <placeName>G&#183;i&#333;&#700;x</placeName>, above <placeName>T&#257;&#700;yaq&#333;&#671;</placeName>."</p>
      <p><pb n="31"/>Then the child went. He would go at once into the water at the lake that was reached first, and he would rub his body with <plant>hemlock</plant>-branches. He followed the advice of his father and his uncles. He did those actions in which he was instructed by his father and his uncles. He went on, and arrived at the lake named <placeName>Qwa&#7499;n&#275;qw&#257;&#700;la</placeName>. The name of the lake of <placeName>G&#183;i&#333;&#700;x</placeName> is <placeName>Qwa&#7499;n&#275;qw&#257;&#700;la</placeName>. The boy went, and came to the shore of the lake. He went right into the water and bathed in the lake. "Evidently this is what my father and uncles referred to," said the boy. "Evidently this is named <placeName>Qwa&#7499;n&#275;qw&#257;&#700;la</placeName>," said the boy. Then the boy swam to an island in the lake in <placeName>Qwa&#7499;n&#275;qw&#257;&#700;la</placeName>. <placeName>Qwa&#7499;n&#275;qw&#257;&#700;la</placeName> is the name of the lake. The nesting-place of all kinds of <animal>birds</animal> is in this lake.</p>
      <p>Then the boy slept. It was just as though he was unconscious [asleep]. Then he heard the sound of paddling. "H&#333;i, h&#333;i," said the noise of the paddles. Behold, it was he who is called <persName>Warrior-of-the-World</persName>. "W&#333;i, w&#333;i," said what was heard by the child on the lake, in <placeName>Qwa&#7499;n&#275;qw&#257;&#700;la</placeName>. Then the boy made up his mind. Then the boy sat down on the island in the lake. The boy just went under water and sat in the water of the lake. While he was sitting there, he listened for the sound of paddling that had been heard to come again, - that which said "W&#333;i, w&#333;i." Soon it approached the place where he was sitting. It came near. Then he went under water, and he looked at it from underneath. He sat under water in the lake. Then he took hold of the canoe of him who is called <persName>Warrior-of-the-World</persName>. He nearly [not] upset the canoe of him who is called <persName>Warrior-of-the-World</persName>. Then the boy put his month out of the water while he was tipping over the canoe of him who is called <persName>Warrior-of-the-World</persName>. One man in the canoe spoke: "What may be the matter with you?" Thus <pb n="33"/>said one man among those who are called Warriors-of-the-World. "Don't do that, my dear!" said another man in the canoe of the Warriors-of-the-World. Then the boy was just entreated. There was nothing that was not said to the boy. The one who is called <persName>Warrior-of-the-World</persName> was afraid that he might be capsized by the boy. "Don't do that, my dear! Now I will give you supernatural power." Thus he was told. Then the boy let go of the canoe of <persName>Warrior-of-the-World</persName>. Then <persName>Warrior-of-the-World</persName> went on, and left the child.</p>
      <p>Then the boy went out of the water. The boy just sat down right on the rock, and felt as though he had to sleep on account of what he had done. Behold! he was dead. He was taken by <persName>Warrior-of-the-World</persName>. Evidently he was given something bad. He was killed by <persName>Warrior-of-the-World</persName>, whom he had almost upset. Then the boy was awakened on the rock. "Oh," he was told, "don't stay thus on the rock!" he was told. Then he uncovered his face, and he just looked about. He looked around to see who had awakened him. He did not see any one who had awakened him. Then he bit a hole in his blanket, and then he discovered a little feather. "What are you doing on the rock?" he said. "Don't merely handle things roughly. I have seen you." Thus said the boy.</p>
      <p>Then he was invited to enter the house of the one who is called <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName>. Then the house of <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName> opened, and the house of <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName> was open. Behold! that was the house of <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName> where the boy had slept. Behold! that was the door of <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName> where he had slept. Then he stood on the floor of the house of <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName>, and he was asked, "What does our friend <pb n="35"/>want?" Thus the boy was told when he was standing on the floor. Then the boy said, "I want to get supernatural power." Thus said the boy. "Go on, take what you desire!" he was told by <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName>. "I desire to be a cannibal. I shall be a cannibal." - "Go on, sit down!" Thus the boy was told.</p>
      <p>Then <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName> took some of his red cedar-bark, and he for whom it was tried by <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName> tried it on. Then <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName> uttered the Cannibal cry and went around his house. "Watch me!" the boy was told. "That is the way you will do." And the boy watched the ways of <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName>. Then he finished what had been the reason of his endeavors. "I do not wish to stay long," said the boy. "I do not wish to be permeated too much by my supernatural power, else those who will praise me will be too much afraid of me." - "Wa! [you will not be]!" thus he was told by <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName>. "Now you shall go home to your house." It was only plaited in at the nape of his neck, what was his Cannibal-pole. Only a small piece of <plant>hemlock</plant> was plaited in at the nape of the neck of the boy. The boy came out of the woods. Then he was expected, and the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la tried to catch him in the great dance from above. <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName> came uttering the Cannibal cry. Behold! they came across dancing the great dance from above. Then they came across. Then they hauled the rope, and the rope reached across. The rope went right across. They were pulling the d&#7431;&#700;nts!&#275;k&#7512;, - the d&#7431;&#700;nts!&#275;q of the war dance. Now they were half across [on the way to] <placeName>Gwa&#700;dz&#275;&#7499;</placeName>.</p>
      <p>They say that <persName>Listened-to</persName> now wished the sea-monster to show itself, when <persName>Listened-to</persName>, the ancestor of the Dz&#257;&#700;wad&#7431;&#275;nox&#7512;, came and was sitting behind them. "Show <pb n="37"/>yourself, sea-monster!" Thus he said. He wished <persName>Q!&#275;&#700;q!&#7431;ls&#7431;la</persName> to show itself at <placeName>Sea-Monster-Place</placeName>. They showed themselves, - <persName>&#7499;y&#257;&#700;x&#183;&#7499;yak&#183;il&#299;&#322;</persName>, <persName>Q!&#275;&#700;q!&#7431;ls&#7431;la</persName>, <persName>W&#257;&#700;wix&#275;ma</persName>, - those whom <persName>Listened-to</persName> wished to show themselves. Therefore an accident happened on the water to the supernatural power, the dance from above, that they tried to show on the water. Then the rope was cut with which they tried to lead the d&#7431;&#700;nts!&#275;q of the war dance. The d&#7431;&#700;nts!&#275;q of the war dance was rising out of the water. Then it was too much, what they were doing on the water, and the box containing the wolf-head masks just floated away. <persName>Listened-to</persName>, the ancestor of the Dz&#257;&#700;wad&#7431;&#275;nox&#7512;, came and looked for it, and found the box containing the wolf-head masks at <placeName>L&#333;l&#7431;la&#700;ts!&#275;</placeName>. That is the place to which the box containing the <animal>wolf</animal> masks floated. It was just stolen by <persName>Listened-to</persName> of the Dz&#257;&#700;wad&#7431;&#275;nox&#7512;. Therefore the ancestors of the Dz&#257;&#700;wad&#7431;&#275;nox&#7512; have the great dance from above. <persName>Listened-to</persName> [only] obtained by theft the box containing the <animal>wolf</animal> masks of those who danced the winter dance, - the box containing the <animal>wolf</animal> masks which had belonged to <persName>Pearl-Maker-Face</persName> and <persName>Copper-Maker-Face</persName>. They had been the owners of the box containing the <animal>wolf</animal> masks.</p>
      <p>Now, the cannibal who had obtained as supernatural power <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName> appeared on the beach. Then he devoured a man. He bolted down a man, although belonging to his own clan. Then it was difficult to catch him, but he was lassoed, and he was caught. Then he entered the house, and he was tied in the house. They took off what was plaited in at the nape of his neck by <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName>, - that little piece of <plant>hemlock</plant> which was plaited in at the nape of his neck by <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName>. Behold! that was called the <pb n="39"/>Cannibal-pole. Then it was put [up, and reached] through [the roof of] the house. A h&#333;&#700;x&#803;&#7512;hok&#7512; was sitting on top of the Cannibal-pole of <persName>Cannibal-at-North-End-of-World</persName>, and the body of the pole was snapping.</p>
      <p>Then he was treated by his tribe. He was feared by his tribe because he was just bolting down the people of his own clan. Therefore his clan was ridiculed. Vomited was the name of this one Cannibal. <persName>Ku&#700;n&#7499;wat&#7431;lag&#183;ilidz&#7431;m</persName> was the name of another Cannibal. Then the ropes with which the Cannibal was tied were broken. He disappeared and did not come again. Then he had disappeared, he who was the ancestor of the K&#183;!&#238;&#700;g&#183;a&#275;n&#244;x&#7512;, a clan of the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la. Ham&#257;&#700;lak&#183;aua&#7499; was the ancestor of those living at <placeName>Having-Humpback-Salmon</placeName>. He brought the great dance from above to <placeName>Gwa&#700;dz&#275;&#7499;</placeName>, where the A&#700;wi&#671;&#7431;la danced the winter dance together. <epimyth>That is the end.</epimyth></p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
