<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Theft of Fire (version 1)</title>
        <editor ref="p:Gifford1471" role="collector">Edward Winslow Gifford</editor>
        <editor ref="p:ThomasWilliams4900" role="informant">Thomas Williams</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML templates, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="14">About 14 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NNA032806</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial (CC BY-NC)</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2023">2023</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Gifford, Edward Winslow (1917): Miwok Myths. Berkeley: University of California Press (UCLA Publications in American Archeology and Ethnology 12,8). Quot. pp. 284-286.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from an informant who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="">
          <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="34">Used to mark animal names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="2">Used to mark plant names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="2">Used to mark colors (adjectives and nouns) mentioned in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="19">Used to mark personal names (usually characters)
                        mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="3">Used to mark named place names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="0">Used to mark comments or asides within the course of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="2">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged using a semantic tagger based on WordNet and self-provided word
                        lists, and were subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>
                        animal</gi>, <gi>plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, and <gi>
                        placeName</gi>, respectively.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CNA29914">Miwok\Central Sierra Miwok</name>
          <date notAfter="1914" notBefore="1913" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1913 and 1914.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>The <color>Black</color> <animal>Geese</animal> asked the <color>White</color> <animal>Geese</animal> to help them. They gathered in the assembly house.</p>
      <p><animal>Lizard</animal> lay on top of the rock and looked into the valley. It was then that he found the fire. He saw the flames issuing from the smoke hole in the top of a large assembly house. Then <animal>Lizard</animal> told <animal>Coyote</animal> that he saw the fire below. <animal>Coyote</animal> doubted him. <animal>Lizard</animal> said, "Come up here on top of the rock, look below, and you will see sparks coming from the assembly house." <animal>Coyote</animal> asked, "Where do you see the fire? I see no fire in that direction." Then <animal>Lizard</animal> said, "Watch. There goes another spark." <animal>Coyote</animal> said to the <animal>Geese</animal>, "It is strange that we cannot see it. He saw it again." The <animal>Geese</animal> did not believe him. They said that he was deceiving them.</p>
      <p>After sundown <animal>Coyote</animal> saw the fire, entered the assembly house, and told everyone about it. <persName>Flute-player</persName> [<animal>Mouse</animal>] said nothing. The people told <persName>Flute-player</persName> to go out and look at the fire. <persName>Flute-player</persName> merely said, "Yes." He took with him four flutes, but told no one <pb n="285"/>when he left. He played two flutes while he journeyed into the valley. When he arrived at the assembly house in the valley, he did not know how to enter. <animal>Bear</animal>, <animal>Rattlesnake</animal>, and <animal>Mountain Lion</animal> guarded the door, so that none might enter. <persName>Flute-player</persName> climbed on top of the assembly house. There he found <animal>Eagle</animal> with his wing over the smoke hole, so that none might enter. <animal>Eagle</animal>, however, slept. <persName>Flute-player</persName> was puzzled, for he did not know how to enter the house undetected. Finally, he cut two feathers from <animal>Eagle</animal>'s wing and thereby entered.</p>
      <p>When he descended into the assembly house, he found the people asleep. He went to the fire and filled two of his flutes with coals. Again he visited the fire, filling two more. He filled four flutes with the fire.</p>
      <p>Then he started for home. All of the people awoke and looked for him. They ran all over the hills, but did not find him. <animal>Eagle</animal> sent in pursuit Wind, then Rain, then Hail. Hail caught <persName>flute-player</persName>. <persName>Flute-player</persName>, however, placed his flutes in the water before Hail caught him. He told Hail that he had nothing. He said that he would take no one's fire. Hail believed him and departed.</p>
      <p><persName>Flute-player</persName> then recovered his flutes and played upon them after Hail departed. He still had his fire. He said to himself, "I have my fire."</p>
      <p>Finally, he arrived at home, arrived with his fire in the four flutes. <animal>Coyote</animal> came down the mountains to search for him, for he feared that someone had killed <persName>Flute-player</persName>. <persName>Flute-player</persName> sent <animal>Coyote</animal> back ahead of him to tell the people that he was returning with the fire. <animal>Coyote</animal> ran back and told the people to gather wood, told them that <persName>Flute-player</persName> was bringing the fire.</p>
      <p><persName>Flute-player</persName> proceeded slowly, so that <animal>Coyote</animal>, becoming impatient, went to meet him again. He met him when he was nearly home. Upon his arrival, <persName>Flute-player</persName> climbed on top of the assembly house. Then he played his flute. Everyone inside was cold. When <persName>Flute-player</persName> finished playing one flute he dropped coals through the smoke hole into the assembly house. Then he started to play a second flute. Before he finished play the second one, <animal>Coyote</animal> interrupted him by shouting. <animal>Coyote</animal> told <persName>Flute-player</persName> to continue playing.</p>
      <p>The people in the middle received the fire; the others received but little fire - the north people, the south people, the east people, and the west people. The west people did not talk very distinctly, because they received so little fire; the east people the same; the north people the same; the south people the same. Those who were close to the <pb n="286"/>fire talked distinctly. <animal>Coyote</animal>, who stayed at the door, received but little fire. He tried to talk, but shouted instead.</p>
      <p>The people in the middle cooked their food. The, others ate theirs raw. They talked different languages from the people in the middle. The west people talked differently; the south people talked differently; the north people talked differently; the east people talked differently. The middle people talked correctly, for they were around the fire. The people who were around the fire cooked their food. The people in the middle obtained the <plant>acorns</plant> and the <plant>manzanita</plant>. The others had nothing to eat. That which they ate was always raw. <epimyth>It was <animal>Coyote</animal>'s fault, that the others talked incorrectly. If <animal>Coyote</animal> had said nothing, all would have received fire. He spoiled the scheme, when he shouted at <persName>Flute-player</persName>, for <persName>Flute-player</persName> stopped. He stopped before he had played the fourth flute and before he had distributed all of the fire.</epimyth></p>
      <p>All of those who received the fire talked the same language. All of those who were close to the fire had the same language. Some received the fire. Some did not receive it. That is why they did not speak the same language.</p>
      <p>
        <epimyth>If <animal>Lizard</animal> had not found the fire, all would have died. He found the fire and saved the people. <animal>Lizard</animal> found the fire below. <persName>Flute-player</persName> went below to steal the fire to save the people from death. <animal>Coyote</animal> shouted to <persName>Flute-player</persName> to drop one coal in front of him. Then he dropped the coal and one went without fire. All of the middle people understand each other. The others do not hear one another very plainly. They would all have talked correctly, if they had all received fire. The people fought each other, because they did not understand each other's speech.</epimyth>
      </p>
      <p>
        <note>The assembly house of the valley people was upon the west side of the <placeName>San Joaquin River</placeName>. The assembly house of the <animal>Geese</animal> was at <placeName>Goodwin's Ranch</placeName>, near <placeName>Montezuma</placeName>, Tuolumne County.</note>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
