<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Woman Kills the Hebu</title>
        <editor ref="p:Roth394" role="collector">Walter E. Roth</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="informant">	- unidentified -</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML templates, digitization infrastructure, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="9">About 9 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NSA010192</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial (CC BY-NC)</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Roth, Walter E. (1915): An Inquiry into the Animism and Folk-Lore of the Guiana Indians. Extract from the Thirteenth Annual Report of the Bureau of American Ethnology, Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office., p. 189.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly (or via the proxy of an interpreter or other immediate intermediary)
                    from an informant who either lived or grew up as a member of a culture whose
                    primary subsistence at the time of recording was or until recently had been
                    hunting, gathering, and/or fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the
                    recording and the relative freedom from external cultural influences. To create
                    a corpus with high representability, multiple versions of the same narrative
                    were omitted, cultural clusters and close cultural relations between two groups
                    were negatively taken into account, and it was aimed for the highest degree of
                    diversity.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="">
          <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="3">Used to mark animal names in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="1">Used to mark plant names in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="0">Used to mark color names (adjectives and nouns) in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="0">Used to mark culturally important characters in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="0">Used to mark named places in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="1">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="0">Used to mark comments or any asides during a narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> are <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">
                        Wikidata</orgName> Q-IDs and refer to their entry.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to glossary entries
                        collected in the FFDB.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occuring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) with no clear systematic.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>In-text explanations by the original editor are set in brackets. In-text
                        additions/excursions by the informant are set in parenthesis.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to hide language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark quoted
                        passages up as <gi>quote</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged with a semantic tagger based on WordNet and on word lists as well as
                        subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>animal</gi> , <gi>
                        plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi> and <gi>placeName</gi>,
                        respectively.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CSA36701">Warao</name>
          <date notAfter="1913" notBefore="1906" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1906 and 1913.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI">
          <list>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">G312</idno>
              <term>G312. Cannibal ogre.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">K800</idno>
              <term>K800. Killing or maiming by deception.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">Q243.2.1</idno>
              <term>Q243.2.1. Attempted seduction punished. (Cf. Q424.3, Q431.5.1, Q469.10.1.)</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">R11.2.2</idno>
              <term>R11.2.2. Abduction by demon.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">S118.2</idno>
              <term>S118.2. Murder by cutting throat.</term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p><anamyth>When going to a party it is customary among us Indians for the man to start early in the morning, leaving his wife to follow in the course of the afternoon. Well now, on one such occasion,</anamyth> after the house-master had left for the drink-feast, another man came and paid the spouse a visit, telling her that she must come with him to his place. She said: "No! You are not my husband, so I cannot do that." But when he threatened to kill her if she refused, she agreed to accompany him, although her little child told her not to go. This man was really a Hebu, and when he arrived with her and the child at his house, he told her she could have whatever she wanted, pointing at the same time to all the dried meat - <animal>game</animal>, <animal>fish</animal>, <animal>bird</animal>, and human flesh - that was hanging around. Picking what she required, she placed it in the pot and this she put on the fire. All the time she was thinking how she could fool the Hebu, so that when he called her to come into his hammock, her plans were quite prepared. She joined him in his hammock, but refused to lie down in it, and when he told her to kiss and coddle him, she said she couldn't do so because he was covered over so much with hair. He told her where to find a <plant>bamboo</plant>-knife, and she commenced shaving his face; while holding up his chin, she stuck the knife into his throat and killed him. Rushing off now with her child, the woman joined her husband at the drink-party, telling him exactly what had happened: how the Hebu had made her come to his house, where she had killed him. And when the sport was finished next morning she took her husband to the scene of the tragedy. As soon as he saw the dead Hebu's body lying in the hammock, he was satisfied that she had told him the truth.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
