<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Story of Haburi</title>
        <editor ref="p:Roth394" role="collector">Walter E. Roth</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="informant">unidentified</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML templates, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="25">About 25 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NSA010140</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial (CC BY-NC)</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2023">2023</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Roth, Walter E. (1915): An Inquiry into the Animism and Folk-Lore of the Guiana Indians. Extract from the Thirteenth Annual Report of the Bureau of American Ethnology, Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office. Quot. pp. 122-125.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from an informant who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="">
          <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="38">Used to mark animal names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="16">Used to mark plant names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="2">Used to mark colors (adjectives and nouns) mentioned in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="60">Used to mark personal names (usually characters)
                        mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="0">Used to mark named place names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="1">Used to mark comments or asides within the course of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="1">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged using a semantic tagger based on WordNet and self-provided word
                        lists, and were subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>
                        animal</gi>, <gi>plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, and <gi>
                        placeName</gi>, respectively.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CSA36701">Warao</name>
          <date notAfter="1913" notBefore="1906" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1906 and 1913.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI">
          <!-- link to our TMI once its online -->
          <list>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">A1251</idno>
              <term>A1251. Creation of man from tree. (Cf. A1236, A1275.6.)</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">A1445.1+WS</idno>
              <term>A1445.1+WS. Origin of canoe.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">A2272+WS</idno>
              <term>A2272+WS. Ducks learn to float from canoe.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">B143.1.3</idno>
              <term>B143.1.3. Warning parrot.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">B211.3.4</idno>
              <term>B211.3.4. Speaking parrot.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">D195</idno>
              <term>D195. Transformation: man to frog. (Cf. B643).</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">D310+WS2</idno>
              <term>D310+WS2. Transformation: jaguar to person.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">D610</idno>
              <term>D610. Repeated transformation. Transformation into one form after another.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">F402.1.4</idno>
              <term>F402.1.4. Demons assume human forms in order to deceive.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">H30</idno>
              <term>H30. Recognition through personal peculiarities</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">H48</idno>
              <term>H48. Animal in human form recognized. (Cf. H64.)</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">H79.3</idno>
              <term>H79.3. Recognition by voice.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">H973</idno>
              <term>H973. Tasks performed by helpful forest spirits.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">K525.1</idno>
              <term>K525.1. Substituted object left in bed while intended victim escapes.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">K800</idno>
              <term>K800. Killing or maiming by deception.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">Q325</idno>
              <term>Q325. Disobedience punished. (Cf. Q431.3, Q451.7.0.2.3, Q456.0.3, Q458.0.2, Q552.1.0.1.1, Q593.)</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">S116.4</idno>
              <term>S116.4. Murder by crushing head.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">T145.1.3</idno>
              <term>T145.1.3. Man married to several sisters.</term>
            </item>
            <item>
              <idno type="TMI">T615</idno>
              <term>T615. Supernatural growth. (Cf. T585.)</term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>Long ago, there were two sisters minding themselves; they had no man to look after them. One day they cut down an <plant latin="Mauritia">ite tree</plant> [Mauritia], from which they commenced to manufacture flour. It was now late, so they left their work and went home. Next morning when they went back, the starch was lying there all ready prepared, and they were much puzzled to know how this came to be so. Next day, the same thing happened-all the <plant latin="Mauritia">ite</plant> starch was found ready; and this happened again, and often. So one night they watched, and about the middle of the night they saw one of the leaves of the neighboring <plant latin="Euterpe sp.">manicole tree</plant> [Euterpe sp.] bend gradually over and over until it touched the cut which they had made in the trunk of the ite <plant latin="Mauritia">ite palm</plant> lying beneath. As soon as the leaf actually touched, both sisters rushed up and caught hold of it, begging it earnestly to turn into a man. It refused at first; but as they begged so earnestly it did so. His name was <persName>Mayara-k&#243;to</persName>. The big [elder] sister was now happy and by-and-bye she had a beautiful baby boy, called <persName>Haburi</persName>.</p>
      <p><pb n="123"/>The two women had their hunting ground near two ponds; one of these ponds belonged to <animal>Tiger</animal>, but the other one was their own, in which they therefore used to fish. And they told <persName>Mayara-k&#243;to</persName> not to go to <animal>Tiger</animal>'s pond. The man, however, said, "Our pond has very few <animal>fish</animal> in it, but <animal>Tiger</animal>'s has plenty. I am going to fish in his." He did so, but <animal>Tiger</animal> came along and caught and killed him for stealing his <animal>fish</animal>. <animal>Tiger</animal> then took <persName>Mayara-k&#243;to</persName>'s shape and form, and returned to the spot where the two women were camped. It was very late when he came and quite <color>dark</color>. With him he brought not only <persName>Mayara-k&#243;to</persName>'s waiyarri [a temporary openwork basket made of <plant>palm</plant>-leaf] but in it the <animal>fish</animal> the latter had stolen before being killed. <animal>Tiger</animal> put down the waiyarri, as is customary, before coming into the house, and after telling them good-night [lit. "I am come"], said he had brought some <animal>fish</animal>. Both women were astonished at the coarse, rough voice. He then said he was much tired, and would lie down in his hammock, telling them that he would nurse <persName>Haburi</persName>, who was accordingly brought to him. He told them also that he was going to sleep, and that they must bring up the <animal>fish</animal> and cook it, but not to mind him. The women cooked the <animal>fish</animal>. When cooked, and while the women were eating it, the man fell asleep and began to snore very curiously and loudly-indeed, so loud that you could have heard him on the other side of the river. And while snoring, he called the father's name-<persName>Mayara-k&#243;to</persName>. The two women looked at each other, and they listened. They said "Our husband never snored like that; he never called his own name before." They therefore stopped eating at once, and told each other that this man could not possibly be their husband. And they pondered as to how they were going to get <persName>Haburi</persName> out of the man's arms where he was resting. Making a bundle of a particular kind of bark, they slipped it under the child and so got him away; then they quickly made off with him while the man was still snoring. With them they also took a wax light and a bundle of firewood.</p>
      <p>While going along, they heard <persName>Wau-uta</persName> singing. <persName>Wau-uta</persName> was a woman in those days, indeed she was a piai woman, and she was just then singing with her shak-shak [rattle]. The two women went on and on, quickly too, for they knew that once they arrived at <persName>Wau-uta</persName>'s place they would be safe. In the meantime, the <animal>Tiger</animal>-man woke up and found the bark bundle in his arms instead of little <persName>Haburi</persName>, and both the sisters gone. So he got angry; he changed back into his <animal>animal</animal> shape, and hurried after them. The women heard him coming and hurried still more. They called out "<persName>Wau-uta</persName>! open the door." "Who is there?" said <persName>Wau-uta</persName>, to which she received reply "It is we; the two sisters." But <persName>Wau-uta</persName> would not open the door. So the mother pinched little <persName>Haburi</persName>'s ears and made him cry. Directly <persName>Wau-uta</persName> heard it she shouted out, "What child is that? Is it a girl or a boy?" "It is my <persName>Haburi</persName>, a boy," was the mother's reply, upon which <persName>Wau-uta</persName> opened the door immediately and said, "Come in! Come in!" Just after they had all got in, <animal>Tiger</animal> arrived and, calling out to <persName>Wau-uta</persName>, asked her where the two women and the baby had gone. But <persName>Wau-uta</persName> lied, telling that she had not seen them, that she had seen no one. <animal>Tiger</animal>, however, could tell by the scent that they were there, so he waited outside, and refused to go away. This vexed <persName>Wau-uta</persName>, who became very angry, and told him that he might just put his head in, and have a look round, and if he saw them, he could eat them if he liked. But the door was covered with pimplers [<plant>thorns</plant>] and as soon as silly <animal>Tiger</animal> put his head in, the old woman closed it, and so killed him. The two sisters remained there, and cried much; they grieved for their husband. They cried so much indeed that <persName>Wau-uta</persName> told them to go into the field, gather some <plant>cassava</plant>, and make a big drink. They accordingly got ready to go, and were about to take <persName>Haburi</persName> with them, but <persName>Wau-uta</persName> said, "No. I am quite able to look after the child in your absence." So they did as they were told and went away to the field.</p>
      <p>In the meantime <persName>Wau-uta</persName> made the child grow all at once into a youth, and gave him the harri-harri to blow and the arrows to shoot. As the mother and aunt <pb n="124"/>were returning with the <plant>cassava</plant>, they heard the music playing and said to themselves, "There was no man or boy there when we left the house; who can it be? It must be a man playing." And though ashamed they went in and saw the youth blowing the harri-harri. As soon as they had taken the quakes [baskets] from off their backs and placed them on the ground, they asked after <persName>Haburi</persName>, but <persName>Wau-uta</persName> said that as soon as they had left for the field, the child had run after them, and she had thought it was still with them. Of course all this was a lie. Old <persName>Wau-uta</persName> was desirous of making <persName>Haburi</persName> grow quickly, with the intention of making him ultimately her lover. She still further deceived the two sisters by pretending to assist in the search which was then undertaken in the surrounding bush, but she took good care to get back to her house first, and told <persName>Haburi</persName> to say she, <persName>Wau-uta</persName>, was his mother, and gave him full directions as to how he must treat her.</p>
      <p><persName>Haburi</persName> was a splendid shot - no <animal>bird</animal> could escape his arrow - and <persName>Wau-uta</persName> directed him to give to her all the big <animal>birds</animal> that he killed, and to his mother and aunt all the little ones, which he had to pollute first by fouling them. The object of this was to make the two sisters so vexed and angry that they would leave the place: but this they would not do; they continued searching the neighborhood for their little child. This sort of thing went on for many days, big <animal>birds</animal> and dirtied little <animal>birds</animal> being presented by <persName>Haburi</persName> to <persName>Wau-uta</persName> and the two women, respectively. <persName>Haburi</persName>, however, did one day miss a <animal>bird</animal> for the first time, his arrow sticking into a branch overhanging a creek where his uncles, the <animal>water-dogs</animal>, used to come and feed. It was a nice cleared space, and here <persName>Haburi</persName> eased himself, covering the dung with leaves. He next climbed the <plant>tree</plant> to dislodge the arrow, but just then the <animal>water-dogs</animal> arrived, and, scenting the air, exclaimed, "What smell is this? That worthless nephew of ours, <persName>Haburi</persName>, must be somewhere about." So they looked around, and down, and up, and finally discovering him on the <plant>tree</plant> branch, ordered him to come down. They then sat him on a bench, and told him he was leading a bad life, that the old woman was not his mother, but that the two younger ones were his mother and aunt, respectively; they furthermore impressed upon him that it was very wicked of him to divide the <animal>birds</animal> so unfairly, and that in future he must do exactly the opposite, giving his real mother, the bigger of the two sisters, the larger <animal>birds</animal>. They told him also to let his real mother know that the way he had hitherto treated her was due entirely to ignorance on his part, and that he was sorry.</p>
      <p>So when <persName>Haburi</persName> got home that day, he carried out the instructions given him by the <animal>water-dogs</animal>, handing the dirtied little <animal>birds</animal> to <persName>Wau-uta</persName>, and making a clean breast of it to his mother. She, poor thing, felt very strange that day, and could not bring herself to speak to him as "my son" all at once, but when he explained that it was only <persName>Wau-uta</persName> who had made him a man quite suddenly, she believed him, and became quite comforted. Old <persName>Wau-uta</persName>, on hearing all this, worked herself into a great passion, and, seizing <persName>Haburi</persName> by the neck, blew into his face [Sect. 85], and told him he must be mad; so angered and upset was she that she could eat nothing at all. She spent all that day and night in nagging him, and telling him he had left his senses. <persName>Haburi</persName> went away next morning as usual, returning late in the afternoon, when he again gave the big <animal>birds</animal> which he had shot to his real mother and the dirtied little ones to <persName>Wau-uta</persName>. The latter, as might have been expected, gave him no peace.</p>
      <p><persName>Haburi</persName>, therefore, made up his mind to get out. So telling his mother that they must all three arrange to get away together, he made a little corial [a dugout canoe] of bees'-wax, and when completed, he left it at the water-side; but, by next morning a <color>black</color><animal>duck</animal> had taken it away. He therefore made another little clay corial, but this was stolen by another kind of <animal>duck</animal>. In the meantime he cut a large field, and cleared it so quickly that the women with their planting could never keep up with him. They required plenty of <plant>cassava</plant> for their proposed journey. At any rate, while the women planted, <persName>Haburi</persName> would often slip away and make a boat, always of a different kind of wood and of varying shape, and just as regularly would a different <pb n="125"/>species of <animal>duck</animal> come and steal it. At last he happened to make one out of the <plant>silk-cotton tree</plant> and this particular one was not stolen. It was thus <persName>Haburi</persName> who first made a boat and taught the <animal>ducks</animal> to float on the surface of the water because it was with his boats that they managed to do it; <apartmyth>indeed, we Warraus say that each <animal>duck</animal> has its own particular kind of boat.</apartmyth></p>
      <p>But what was more curious, the last boat to be manufactured was found next morning to be very much bigger than it was the night before. <persName>Haburi</persName> told his mother and her sister to collect all the provisions and put them aboard in anticipation of their long journey. He himself returned to the field, bringing the <plant>cassava</plant> cuttings for old <persName>Wau-uta</persName> to plant in their respective holes, and so they both continued working hard. By and bye, he slipped away, went back to the house, took his arrows and ax, and proceeded down to the water-side. But before he left the house, he told the posts not to talk, for in those days the posts of a house could speak [Sect. 169], and if the owner were absent a visitor could thus find out his whereabouts. There was a <animal>parrot</animal>, however, in the house, and <persName>Haburi</persName> quite forgot to warn him to keep silent. So when the old woman after a time found herself alone, she went back to the house, and seeing no <persName>Haburi</persName>, asked the posts whither he had gone; they remained silent. The <animal>parrot</animal>, however, could not help talking, and told her.</p>
      <p><persName>Wau-uta</persName> thereupon rushed down to the landing, arriving there just in time to see <persName>Haburi</persName> stepping into the boat to join his mother and aunt. She seized hold of the craft, screaming "My son! My son! you must not leave me so. I am your mother," and though they all repeatedly struck her fingers with their paddles, and almost smashed them to pieces on the gunwale, she would not let go her hold. So poor <persName>Haburi</persName> had perforce to land again and with old <persName>Wau-uta</persName> proceeded to a large hollow <plant>tree</plant> wherein the <animal>bees</animal> had built their nest. Cutting down the <plant>tree</plant>, <persName>Haburi</persName> made a small hole in the trunk, and told the old lady to get in and suck the honey. She was very fond of honey, and though crying very hard all the time at the thought of losing <persName>Haburi</persName>, crawled through the little opening which he immediately closed in upon her. <epimyth>And there she is to be found to the present day, the <persName>Wau-uta</persName> <animal>frog</animal> which is heard only in hollow <plant>trees</plant>. And if you look carefully, you will see how swollen her fingers are from the way in which they were bashed by the paddles when she tried to hold on to the gunwale. If you listen, you can also hear her lamenting for her lost lover; she still cries Wang! Wang! Wang!</epimyth></p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
