<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/Schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/Schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Origin of the Caribs (Warrau version)</title>
                <editor ref="p:Roth394" role="collector">Walter E. Roth</editor><editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="informant">	- unidentified -</editor><funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
                <principal>
                    <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
                    <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>XML templates, digitization infrastructure, and automated inline tagging</resp>
                    <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>
                <measure unit="KB" quantity="11">About 11 kilobytes</measure>
            </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
                <idno type="FFDB">NSA010026</idno>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial (CC BY-NC)</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Roth, Walter E. (1915): An Inquiry into the Animism and Folk-Lore of the Guiana Indians. Extract from the Thirteenth Annual Report of the Bureau of American Ethnology, Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, pp. 143-144.</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly (or via the proxy of an interpreter or other immediate intermediary)
                    from an informant who either lived or grew up as a member of a culture whose
                    primary subsistence at the time of recording was or until recently had been
                    hunting, gathering, and/or fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the
                    recording and the relative freedom from external cultural influences. To create
                    a corpus with high representability, multiple versions of the same narrative
                    were omitted, cultural clusters and close cultural relations between two groups
                    were negatively taken into account, and it was aimed for the highest degree of
                    diversity.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="">
                    <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="6">Used to mark animal names in the text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="6">Used to mark plant names in the text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="0">Used to mark color names (adjectives and nouns) in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="0">Used to mark culturally important characters in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="0">Used to mark named places in the text.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="0">Used to mark comments or any asides during a narrative.</tagUsage>
                    <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
                    <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
                    <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> are <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">
                        Wikidata</orgName> Q-IDs and refer to their entry.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
                    <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to glossary entries
                        collected in the FFDB.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
                <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occuring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) with no clear systematic.</p>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>In-text explanations by the original editor are set in brackets. In-text
                        additions/excursions by the informant are set in parenthesis.</p>
                    <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to hide language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <quotation marks="all">
                    <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark quoted
                        passages up as <gi>quote</gi>.</p>
                </quotation>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged with a semantic tagger based on WordNet and on word lists as well as
                        subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>animal</gi> , <gi>
                        plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi> and <gi>placeName</gi>,
                        respectively.</p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="culture" key="CSA36701">Warao</name>
                    <date notAfter="1913" notBefore="1906" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1906 and 1913.</date>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        <textClass><keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI"><list><item><idno type="TMI">A1611.1</idno><term>A1611.1. Origin of American Indian tribes.</term></item><item><idno type="TMI">B610.1</idno><term>B610.1. Girl's animal lover slain by spying relatives.</term></item><item><idno type="TMI">B613.1</idno><term>B613.1. Snake paramour. (Cf. B604.1.)</term></item><item><idno type="TMI">C141.3</idno><term>C141.3. Tabu: not to enter water during menses.</term></item><item><idno type="TMI">C900</idno><term>C900. Punishment for breaking tabu.</term></item><item><idno type="TMI">D391</idno><term>D391. Transformation: serpent (snake) to person.</term></item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
    <body>
<p>A Warrau man warned his sister not to bathe in a certain neighboring pond at those regular periods when she happened to be unwell [Sect. 188]. For a long time she obeyed his instructions, but after a time, forgetting all about them, she went to bathe at the forbidden spot and time, and was caught by a large <animal>snake</animal>, the water-camudi Uamma. By and by she became pregnant. Now it was during the <plant latin="Mimusops belata">bullet-tree</plant> [Mimusops belata] season, when the Indians used to cut down the <plant>trees</plant> to secure the seed, which are excellent eating, and it was noticed that this same woman, although she took no ax away with her in the morning, invariably returned with a large quantity of the delicious seed in the afternoon. The brother, thereupon becoming suspicious, watched her. Unobserved himself, he followed her next day, saw her approach a huge <plant>bullet-tree</plant>, and saw the Uamma <animal>snake</animal> [Sect. 244] sneaking out of the woman's body, coil around the <plant>tree</plant>, and make his way up into the topmost branches. There the <animal>snake</animal> changed into a man, who shook the boughs for the woman, thus causing the seeds to fall to the ground, where she gathered them. Having done this, the Uamma, reverting to his original form, descended the <plant>tree</plant>, and again <pb n="144"/>entered the woman's body. Thereupon the brother said, "There is something wrong here; this will not do: My sister probably has a <animal>snake</animal> in her body." So he told his friends who, in company with him, watched his sister the next day, when the same thing took place, Uamma sneaking out below the woman's body, climbing the <plant>tree</plant>, changing into human form, shaking the seeds down, and then becoming a <animal>snake</animal> again. But just as Uamma was about to reach the ground, the watchers rushed up and cut him into thousands of pieces. The woman grieved sorely, but collected all the fragments under a heap of mold and leaves, each piece of which by and by grew into a Carib. Many years passed; the Caribs growing strong and numerous, became a nation. They lived in harmony with the Warraus, so much so that when one tribe caught some game or other dainty, they would send a child with a piece of it over to the Warraus. The latter would then return the compliment and send a child of theirs with food to the Caribs. This lasted a long time, until one day the original mother of the Caribs - a very old woman now - told them to kill the child which the Warraus had sent to them; this was in revenge for the way the Warraus had slain her <animal>snake</animal> lover years before. As might have been expected, the Warraus on the next occasion slaughtered the Carib child, and thus a blood feud arose between the two nations, the Caribs finally overwhelming the Warraus.</p>
</body></text>
</TEI>
